Finding Aid for Howard Y. McClusky Papers 1921-1982
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Topical Files circa 1938-1978
  - National Council for the Panel of Americans 1954-1960 (Box 11)
  - National Council on Religion in Higher Education 1947-1952, 1958 (Box 11)
  - National Education Association 1948, 1950-1952, 1968 (Box 11)
  - National Planning Association 1947-1949 (Box 11)
  - National Social Welfare Assembly 1952-1953, 1960 (Box 11)
  - National Training Laboratories 1957-1961 (Box 11)
  - Navy Conference Research Project 1947-1948 (Box 11)
  - Neighborhood War Clubs 1942-1944, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - New York State Citizens Council 1947-1957 (Box 11)
  - Rural Youth, Miscellaneous (Box 12)
  - Senate Advisory Committee on University Affairs 1959-1961 (Box 12)
  - Sexual Deviates, Governor's Study Commission on 1950 (Box 12)
  - Teaching Learning Communities, the Institute of 1976-1980, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - UNESCO, Michigan Council for 1949-1959 (scattered) (Box 12)
  - University of British Columbia 1973-1978 (Box 12)
  - Youth
    - General (Box 12)
    - Michigan (Box 12)
  - War Problems 1942-1944 (Box 12)
  - White House Conference on Aging 1971 (Box 12)
  - Writings
    - By Others (Box 12)
    - Unidentified (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
- Visual Materials
  Most of the photos are of McClusky, alone and in groups, formal and informal. Most are unlabeled. There are many pictures of him in the classroom and on the speaker's platform. The photos from the Conference of the organization for Community Self Help are fully and informatively captioned.
  - Photographs
    - Of Howard McClusky
      - Portraits undated (Box 12)
      - Family and candid undated (Box 12)
      - In Classroom and with Students undated, 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Speaking Engagements (Box 12)
      - In Groups
        - Identified, 2 folders (Box 12)
        - Unidentified (Box 12)
  - Scrapbook: Conference of Organization for Community Self-Help
    - April 1949, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Videotape
    - Interviews on "lifelong learning" and "community development" (VHS tape) (Box 13)
- Sound Tapes
  Some of the tapes are unidentifiable because of their fragility or the speed at which they were recorded. Arrangements can be made, however, to listen to these tapes if required by the researcher. Most of the identifiable tapes are addresses given by McClusky on adult education and community development. (Several tapes of McClusky family dinner conversation, hymn singing, and church sermons were returned to the family.)
  Because there is not much manuscript material on the subject, the tape of McClusky's evaluation of the Upper Peninsula Committee on Area Progress (UPCAP) is most noteworthy. McClusky considered this effort at regional community development to be among his most important projects. Also interesting is the panel of students from Lebanon, India, and Holland, discussing their nations' adult education programs. The interview with George Romney, though not conducted by McClusky, pertains largely to Citizens for Michigan, for which McClusky was director of area 10.
  - McClusky
    - Addresses
      - "Constructive Use of Change in a Changing World," (audience of public school teachers and administrators), circa 1958, 7"; 7-1/2 ips. (Box 13)
        (audio tape no. 1)
      - "Approaches to Community Development" and panel discussion "Trends in Community Development," Community Development Seminar September 1960, 7"; 3.75 ips. (Box 13)
        (audio tape nos. 2-3)
      - (?), Community School Conference ("Durant-Turri-Mott") October 1961, 7"; 3.75 ips. (Box 13)
        (audio tape no. 4)
      - Evaluation of "UPCAP" Activities, Annual Meeting of Upper Peninsula Committee on Area Progress, Houghton, Michigan June 1968, 5"; 3.75 ips. (Box 13)
        (audio tape no. 5)
      - Adult Education and the Community School, Phi Delta Kappa Conference, West Haven, Connecticut October 1968, 5"; 3.75 ips. (Box 13)
        (audio tape no. 6)
      - Summer Adult Education Conference, University of Wisconsin, Milwaukee 1970, 6"; 3.75 ips. (Box 13)
        (audio tape no. 7)
      - Community Education Workshop, n.p. undated, 7"; 3.75 ips. (Box 13)
        (audio tape no. 8)
      - "Cooperative Community of Tomorrow," National Community School Clinic undated, 7" 3.75 ips. (Box 13)
        (audio tape no. 9)
      - How to Start a Community Council (incomplete), n.p. undated, 7"; 7-1/2 ips. (Box 13)
        (audio tape no. 10)
    - Classroom
      - H120: Adult Education Methods, circa 1954, 7"; fragile (Box 13)
        (audio tape no. 11)
      - [untitled] re problem of non-participants in discussion, 7"; 7-1/2 ips. (Box 13)
        (audio tape no. 12)
      - [untitled], 7"; 7-1/2 ips. (Box 13)
        (audio tape no. 13)
  - Others
    - Adult Education
      - Robert Petrosky, Adult Education Meeting undated, 7"; 7-1/2 ips. (Box 13)
        (audio tape nos. 14-15)
      - "The Good Look": script for filmstrip, 7"; 7-1/2 ips. (Box 13)
        (audio tape no. 16)
      - "Adult Education Around the World": panel discussion of U M students from Beirut, Bombay, and Amsterdam), 7"; 7-1/2 ips. (Box 13)
        (audio tape no. 17)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Langsburg Community Council (?), panel presentation re school improvements undated, 7"; 7-1/2 ips. (Box 13)
        (audio tape no. 18)
      - Glenford Mitchell, Secretary of National B'hai Spiritual Assembly, re Five Year Youth Program Conference 1968, 5"; 3.75 ips. (Box 13)
        (audio tape no. 19)
      - Junior Achievement and Conservation, interview on WHVR, Ann Arbor, with JA member undated, 5"; 7-1/2 ips. (Box 13)
        (audio tape no. 20)
      - George Romney, interview re Citizens for Michigan, n.p. undated, 7"; 7-1/2 ips. (Box 13)
        (audio tape no. 21)
      - "Some Facts About Aging," produced by P. Hobson and D. Zarlengo, n.p. undated, cassette (Box 13)
        (audio tape no. 22)
      - Michigan University Community and Adult Education Department, report (?), various unidentified speakers (incomplete) undated, cassette (Box 13)
        (audio tape no. 23)
      - Developing a Community Library, n.p. undated, 7"; 7-1/2 ips. (Box 13)
        (audio tape no. 24)
- Miscellaneous
  Miscellaneous is a small unprocessed grouping of McClusky materials that were accumulated by his colleague Larry Berlin. Much of this series is probably duplicated in other series of the collection.
  - McClusky materials accumulated by Larry Berlin, 1 linear feet (Box 13)
    (include reports and published materials relating to community adult education)